What's this?
這是什麼
νοῦς
νοῦς
Nous...
魂形…
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
Fallaina the Nous.
魂形·法萊那
Isn't nous...
魂形不是…
that strange creature in Lykos' island...
黎可斯的島上的 那個奇怪的…
We have a nous here in the mud whale too?
泥鯨上也有魂形的嗎？
Nous is something works like the heart for the ship on the sea of sand.
魂形就好比沙海之上的船舶的心臟
If the nous has been destroyed, the mud whale will sink.
只要破壞魂形 泥鯨就會沉沒
Neli?
奈莉？
In the end you have found here...
還是讓你進到這裡來了嗎…
The girl on the island, you must know what it is.
島上的少女啊…還是讓你知道了
But, it's too late...
但是 已經遲了
Go! For the sake of the mud whale!
給我上！ 為了泥鯨！
No!
不行
Nooo!
不行！
Translator
翻
ssnake
譯
静寂よ　旋律よ　儚き印よ
ssnake
Silence and melody, and the transient lives of Shirushi
静寂よ　旋律よ　儚き印よ
Timing
時 間 軸
zwc1991
zwc1991
砂上にこの地に　生き続けたのなら
砂上にこの地に　生き続けたのなら
If you have been living on the land, on the sea of sand
如果是在這沙海之上  生活下去
罪を纏う世界から　鯨の歌を聴いた...
罪を纏う世界から　鯨の歌を聴いた…
In a sinned world, we have heard the whale's lied
在罪業重重的世界裡  我們曾側耳傾聽鯨魚的歌唱…
運命を　感情を　抱くべき子たちよ
運命を　感情を　抱くべき子たちよ
Our fate and our emotions, my beloved children
不論命運  還是感情  親愛的孩子們喲
さ  き
さ  き
その先へ　その未来へ
その先へ　その未来へ
Towards the future, go ahead
向著未來  向著前方
導かれたのなら
導かれたのなら
If you can be our guide
只要有你指引前路
幾千の声　空想の地へ
幾千の声　空想の地へ
Thousands of words, leaving for the fantasy lands
萬千寄語  向著空想的彼岸
舵を切って行こうとした
舵を切って行こうとした
Steering towards the opposite
相信信念調轉方向
バラード
バラード
幾千の声　砂の海の譚歌
幾千の声　砂の海の譚歌
Thousands of songs, they are the ballads of the sea of sand
萬千歡聲  是沙海的歌謠
F
雪 飄 工 作 室
L
雪 飄 工 作 室
What the hell this time!
這次是怎麼搞的！
How can the mud whale shake like this...
泥鯨居然搖晃的這麼厲害
What!
怎麼了！
So it started.
開始了嗎
Oops.
哎呀
Don't stop it!
可別停手啊
Everyone will die after a few hours.
再過幾個小時大家就都死了
Let's enjoy our playing until the very end!
讓我們就這麼玩耍到最後的一分一秒吧
So it's really going to sink?
這裡真的要沉沒了嗎
Yeah.
是啊
Everybody will die.
大家都要去死
Are you OK with that!
你就這麼接受了嗎！
OK or not,
不管我接不接受
Do you really care yourself that much?
倒是你對你自己就這麼留戀嗎
For me, I don't.
我是一點也不的
It's hard to live.
活著是如此艱辛
Human being is a burdensome creature.
人是種麻煩的生物
The heart...
因為心…
The heart is annoying!
因為心靈是那麼礙手礙腳
Free us, with the power of the sand.
解放我們吧 以沙的力量
We will be saved from the suffering lives!
從人生的苦痛之中 拯救你我！
Don't judge it by your own!
不關你的事
What you want to throw away is yours...
你想拋棄的 是你的…
is your own world!
只屬於你的世界
That's not my world.
不是我的世界
I will decide it myself!
我的事情 我自己來決定！
We were born and raised on the mud whale,
我們在泥鯨上出生在泥鯨上長大
in such a small world.
在這個小小的世界裡
What shocked us the most after we knew the world outside,
知曉外面的世界 對我們來說最為震懾的
is that outside the island,
是在這個小島之外
there are traces that people dying and living.
還有著許許多多的人生軌跡 在激流中交織飛舞
And they are not simply the traces,
這並不只是他們的軌跡
but spectacular records that are swirling and sparkling.
而是燦爛而激越的 博大的記錄
Therefore, we scared.
所以我們感到害怕
We are afraid how people... and the records had disappeared in a moment.
到底發生什麼事… 會讓人 會讓這些記錄在一瞬之間消失
It's not enough!
繼續！
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
We must kill Fallaina completely!
必須要徹底了結法萊那的生命！
Lykos!
黎可斯！
Shoot!
快射！
No matter how sad, how painful it is,
不管懷著多麼痛苦 多麼悲傷的思念
I will never resign my work as a recorder.
我也不願放棄 我作為記錄者的人生
We are...
我們還
We are not yet to finish our records!
不想終結 我們的人生
Lykos!
黎可斯！
Stop it...
住手…
It's already enough!
已經夠了吧！
You idiot!
你們這些白痴！
How could you hurt our friend?
怎麼能傷害伙伴呢！
But...
咦…
Since the minute she was on the mud whale,
只要上了泥鯨這艘船
she became our friend, isn't it!
就是我們的伙伴了 不是嗎！
Why...
為什麼
Why does a person from our mother country try to stop us?
為什麼祖國的人會阻止我們
Isn't you a soldier with the mission to kill us all?
你不是來消滅我們的士兵嗎
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
You know if Fallaina is destroyed,
只要破壞法萊那 泥鯨和這裡的人民都會一起沉沒
What?
哎？
Isn't that your aim?
這不正是 你們所希望的嗎
For me,
我並…
I don't want that...
不希望…這樣
You are... not... sinners...
你們…並不是…罪人
You own something... that we lost...
你們身上有著…我們所失卻的…
Something important...
重要的東西
You are the hope... of this world...
你們是…這個世界的希望
I believe it... now...
我如今…是這麼想的…
Lykos!
黎可斯！
You... you say we are the hope?
你…你說我們是希望？
Impossible!
不可能
We have being carrying our sins... for a hundred years...
百年以來…我們一直背負著我們的罪業
Unless we die... There is no way
除了自絕於人間
for us to escape from this burden!
我們還能怎樣擺脫這個重擔！
Because we are the sinners!
因為我們是罪人！
It's not something you can decide!
這種事誰說了都不算的啊！
Did you presbyters think Taisha-sama, Sami and anyone else
長老們難道覺得 台霞姐姐和莎米他們
deserve their deaths since they are the sinners?
都是罪人 所以死了
Did you think they are culpable of deaths?
也是罪有應得嗎
I don't know what happened long long ago.
過去的事情我不知道
Although those who attacked here
襲擊這裡的人們
also mentioned that there is no hope for us,
也說我們沒有希望
Lykos, who come from the world outside,
但從外面的世界來的黎可斯
becomes to love the mud whale.
能喜歡上泥鯨
Isn't that our hope!
這不就是我們的希望嗎
The people from the world outside will
總有一天 外面的世界的人們
understand us one day.
也會理解我們
Isn't it better to think this way?
難道我們不能這麼想嗎
As long as we have some hopes,
明明還有希望…
I don't want to run away from the hope!
不想逃避希望啊！
I will protect Lykos and everybody else absolutely!
我絕對會保護好黎可斯還有大家！
Shut up!
閉嘴
Get out here!
給我讓開！
No!
不讓！
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
Go! Kill Fallaina!
快！幹掉法萊那
What're you doing here!
還愣著幹什麼！
Let me have a look.
給我看看
You must receive some treatment now.
得趕緊處理
Be at ease.
別擔心
Most of us Muin were medical staffs.
我們無印大多都有醫療工作經驗
Shira'ai-sama! Nashiji-sama!
希拉艾奶奶！納西吉爺爺！
Sorry, Hakuji.
哈庫奇 對不起了
Bring her to the medical office!
把她送到醫務室去
Bear it a little more.
再忍一下
Why, why you don't understand...
為什麼…為什麼你們不懂
I know it's not an easy decision...
這並不是輕易能做出的決斷
But didn't you make up your minds?
但你們不是已經做好覺悟了嗎
Hakuji...
哈庫奇…
I invited them here.
是我請他們來的
Why...
為什麼…
I have given you a hard time...
一直以來讓你困擾了呢
Sorry.
對不起啊
Mom...
「媽媽」…
The shake... has stopped?
不搖晃了？
So he had done it.
那傢伙 做到了嗎
Disappointing.
什麼啊
The elderly must be scared at the last minute.
爺爺們最後關頭又害怕了嗎
What's happened with your eye?
你這眼睛…
It's a fake paradise here.
這裡是虛偽的樂園
Everything is going to decay like this.
一切都像這樣日漸腐朽
Children of the whale are born with this curse.
鯨魚的孩子們從出生之時起就背負著詛咒
It would be much easier to throw
像這樣腐壞的身體 不需要的心靈
Let's play next time.
下次再跟你一決勝負
Since we still have to live,
既然人生未盡
I have to stock some fun to have it later.
那麼總要給自己留點快樂
I don't want to have a boring live.
我可不想無聊地活下去
What was that shake?
怎麼搞的 剛才那陣搖晃
It's broken.
壞了
That's the tool to destroy the lock of prison!
破壞監獄門鎖的道具
What should we do then, we can't save Suo now!
這下該怎麼辦 救不了蘇澳了！
Cuz you fell down on it.
都怪你壓過來了
Lose some weight!
給我減減肥
S... Stop it!
討…討厭
Hakuji-sama...
哈庫奇爺爺…
I have been closing my heart and ruling others with my mind for a long time.
長期以來 我以己律人 封閉自己的內心
I thought it was for the sake of everybody, but it's not...
出於好心做的事情 反而事與願違…
We don't know what to do now.
我們已經 不知道該如何是好了
What should we do for the island, for everyone...
這個島 還有大家 該如何是好
Fine.
好了
Drink this, and you will get calm.
把這個喝了 能讓你平靜下來
I promise we will not confine you in your room anymore.
我保證再也不會把你關在房裡了
Be easy and have a rest.
安心休息吧
We have to go.
我們得去
We have to talk with each other.
我們得去把話說開了
But what should we...
但是該怎麼辦
After the group suicide have been turned down, what should we...
既然集體自殺這條路已經走不通了 我們該…
What should our children do?
孩子們該怎麼辦才好
Have you seen Neli?
看到奈莉了沒？
No.
沒有
Where did her go?
她去哪了呢
There are lots of things I want to ask her...
明明有很多事情想問她的
But it's nice to have the mud whale saved.
太好了 泥鯨沒有沉沒
Chakuro!
查克羅
Congratulations! Our new chief!
恭喜就任首長
That suits you, Su~o~sa~ma~
好配你呢 蘇～澳～小～哥～哥～
From today, we are your aides.
今天開始我們就是服侍您左右的助手了
But...
但是…
You were the aides of Taisha-sama...
你們不是台霞姐姐的…
Actually you have to appoint the new aides~
本來助手也該重新選的〜
But we are in an emergency~
不過如今情況特殊〜
We haven't got the permission of the presbytery.
雖然還沒有獲得長老會的許可
But it's just fine to report it later.
不過這種事情事後再報告就好了
Thank you.
拜託各位了
Um... Though I am still inexperienced...
那個…雖然我還不夠成熟
We can't have an inexperienced chief at such a time!
這種時候首長怎麼能不成熟
You will be dismissed immediately if you don't have the ability.
不行的話馬上卸任
Dang, Kuchiba you are too straight.
哎呀 庫奇巴你這麼露骨
It isn't straight, but obviously...
什麼叫露骨啊 這不是理所當然…
You're completely different before Taisha-sama.
和對台霞姐姐的態度完全不一樣
Sh...Shut up!
真…真多嘴
Let's go, Suo~
噢 蘇澳我們走吧～
Huh? Where?
咦 去哪裡啊
To see Lykos.
黎可斯那裡
She said she would tell us something important.
她說她有重要的事情要告訴我們
But how about the presbytery?
長老會那邊呢
What? How innocent you are!
什麼 你也真是個老好人
We'll report it later, too.
這個也事後再報告
To be honest, I couldn't trust the presbytery anymore after this time.
老實說 這次事情之後就對長老會失去信任了
Even I understand they are for the sake of mud whale...
雖然知道他們也是為了泥鯨好
But it's not good to split up under such an emergency.
但是這種時候內部再搞分裂好嗎
We just get the information first.
我們只是先去獲得情報
Fortunately that girl seems to be off her guard with Chakuro.
幸好那姑娘似乎對查克羅沒什麼警惕
In other words, Lykos is in our hands.
也就是 可以說黎可斯在我們的掌控之中
I thought the aides of chief follow the presbytery.
我本以為首長的助手是唯長老會馬首是瞻的
It's different this time~
這次不一樣〜
It's for the sake of everyone on the mud whale.
為了泥鯨的百姓
For our people, the presbytery and we are under the same principle.
這一點 我們和長老會是一致的
νοῦς
νοῦς
Nous...?
魂形…？
The presbytery tried to sink the mud whale by destroying that, you mean...
長老們打算破壞掉它 讓泥鯨沉沒 嗎
Yes.
是的
Every ship has a nous!
所有的船上都是有魂形的
So we can fight the enemies off if we can destroy their nous!
也就是說 只要破壞掉敵人的魂形就能擊退他們了
Ah, but... that means,
啊 但是這樣一來
The people from Lykos' country will sink in the sand...
黎可斯你們國家的人就會沉入沙海了
No problem.
沒關係
They have their means to return to the mother ship.
他們有回到母船去的手段
They even have a mother ship?
還有母船的嗎！
σκύλος
σκύλος
But if they lose the Skulax,
不過 損失斯奇洛斯
it would be pretty painful for them.
對他們來說也是一個沉重的打擊
Your country has only one battleship
小姐姐你們國家的戰艦
called the Sukilosu, right?
只有那個「司其螺絲」這一艘嗎
Shut up! Don't break in!
你別插嘴！
It should be fine!
不行嗎
I think it is fine.
我不反對
To fulfill the plan of Chakuro,
為了實現查克羅的計劃
we need as much wisdom as possible.
我們需要儘可能多的智慧
Do you really think Masoo has wisdom?
你覺得瑪索腦子裡有智慧嗎
Shut up! You should die out!
閉嘴 你這該死的
Get to sleep until you recover from your injury!
治好傷之前給我安份點
I've already recovered!
早就治好了
You should shut up! You meathead!
倒是你給我閉嘴 豬腦子
Lykos, let's continue.
黎可斯 請繼續
νοῦς
νοῦς
There are 8 ships equipped with nous in the empire.
帝國擁有的魂形的船 一共有8艘
There are as many as 8 big ships like that!
那麼大的船竟然有8艘嗎
Is that true?
真的假的
I mean there are only 8.
是只有8艘
Nous is a creature that absorbs emotions from human beings.
魂形是以人的感情為食的生物
Those who own nous are able to control the minds of people.
只要擁有魂形 就能支配人的心靈
Therefore, my brother...
所以 哥哥…
νοῦς
νοῦς
λύκος
λύκος
They decided to secure Lykos the Nous first.
他們才以回收「魂形·黎可斯」為優先事項
Your ship was wrecked, and your fellows had been killed.
黎可斯你們的船被弄得破破爛爛 你的伙伴們都死掉了是怎麼回事？
Who did that?
那是誰做的
A ship from the enemy state.
是跟帝國敵對的國家的船
There are still other countries!
還有其他的國家嗎
There are several.
有好幾個
There are as many as 8 ships that big.
那麼大的船居然有8艘
There are numbers of guys like soldiers.
士兵什麼的有那麼多
And there is a country where they belong to.
有能管理他們的國家
There is an enemy state.
還有敵對的國家
And there are even more countries?
然後還有別的國家嗎？
I start to have a headache...
頭痛起來了
Amazing!
好棒…
I will tell Oni afterwards.
之後也要告訴歐尼
So... They are our enemies.
這些就是 我們的敵人對吧
Only the empire wants to destroy the mud whale.
想要摧毀泥鯨的只有帝國
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
Since other countries don't even know about the existence of Fallaina.
其他的國家就連法萊那的存在都不知道
Why does the empire want to...
為什麼帝國要破壞泥鯨…
destroy the mud whale, Fallaina?
要破壞法萊那呢？
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
νοῦς
νοῦς
Because Fallaina is different from other nous.
因為法萊那和其他的魂形不同
What's the difference?
不同是？
It can't absorb the feelings of people.
它不能吃人的感情
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
νοῦς
νοῦς
Just like Fallaina is a heterogeneous nous different from the others,
就像法萊那是特殊的 和別的魂形不同一樣
your ancestors are also...
你們的祖先 也是…
What?
哎？
νοῦς
νοῦς
It is said that your ancestors refused to be ruled by nous,
你們的祖先 據說是拒絕為魂形所支配
and chose to keep their own feelings.
選擇繼續擁有感情的人
So the empire was using
所以帝國以
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
Fallaina, which can't fulfill its original purpose of absorbing feelings,
不能實現其原本目的「吃掉感情」的法萊那為牢籠
as a prison, to keep you imprisoned on the sea of sand.
想把你們 封閉在沙海之中
We were... I was told that
我們…我被教育說
the savages living with their own feelings
法萊那是放任自己的感情的野蠻的一族
live with suspicions and hates, in a small ship called Fallaina.
在小船之中過著互相憎惡 互相猜疑的生活
That was a island like a living hell.
那樣一個宛如人間地獄一般的小島
But since the enemy state has got the technology to travel over the sea of sand,
在敵國得到了在沙海中航行的技術的如今
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
we can't give them the opportunity of seizing Fallaina.
不能讓他們奪取法萊那
However the empire
但是帝國也
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
fallaina
無法接受和承認法萊那以及鯨的罪人
So they have decided...
於是決定了…
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
to annihilate the Fallaina, and to massacre all the ...
破壞法萊那 以及全體罪人後裔的
descendants of the sinners.
死刑
B...But
但 但是
There are definitely people who are not our enemy somewhere!
不與我們為敵的人 也一定在什麼地方存在著的吧
Somewhere in the world outside!
在外面的世界的某個地方
Perhaps...
或許
But I'm not familiar with the other countries...
但是我對其他國家的事情…
Well, a world full of enemies, and a world not
不過是與世界為敵 還是並非如此
are totally different.
是完全不一樣的
The enemy's enemy is our friend.
敵人的敵人就是朋友
It is possible that somebody in the world
世界之中或許有人能發現泥鯨
will find us mud whale and accept our existence.
能接受我們的存在
Lykos...
黎可斯
Do you think we are able to wait until that time?
我們能夠等到那一刻嗎
But you'll have to endure the attacks from the empire before that...
在那之前 我們得先抵禦住帝國的襲擊
Do you think we can fight with hope
在這個世界中找到我們的「伙伴」之前
until we finally find our companion in the world?
你覺得我們能夠胸懷希冀堅持戰鬥嗎？
If that's what you want,
如果這是你們的願景
I would...
我願意…
I would stake my life to cooperate with you.
奉獻我的一切幫助你們
There is a speech from the new chief.
說是新首長有話要跟大家說
I wonder what was the shake yesterday...
昨天那個搖晃到底是怎麼回事啊
The new chief is there!
新首長來了
It's Suo!
是蘇澳
I still believe what Lykos has told us,
黎可斯所說的世界的真實
is not the entire of the truth of the world.
在我看來還不完整
For the empire, our existence
對帝國來說 我們的存在
should have more meaning than wanting to wipe us out.
應該還有想要消滅之上的意義
Anyway,
但是至少
it is true that we have hopes!
我們是毫無疑問還有希望的
Listen!
各位！
The sun has never betrayed us for even a single day!
太陽日復一日
The stars have never betrayed us for a single year!
星光年復一年
They have never forgot to bring grace to us.
始終不忘給予我們恩澤
Their mercy will never come to an end.
這份恩澤 從來沒有中斷過
Neither the heaven nor the sand has cursed even a single person.
不論蒼穹還是風沙 都斷然不會詛咒人類
It's unbelievable that the presbytery has permitted such an assembly.
難得長老會能同意這樣一個集會呢
Suo, do your best~
蘇澳 加油啊～
I am going to talk about the status we are,
現在要告訴各位的 是我們如今所處的狀況
and what should we do now in my opinion.
以及我所判斷的我們應該採取的措施
Recently, we had a disaster.
前幾天 我們遭受了慘痛的災難
I believe
在各位當中
some of you here are still in sorrow.
相信還有人依然沉浸於悲痛之中
Unfortunately, it is not the end.
但是遺憾的是 這並不是最後的災難
We have got information that they will attack again after 4 days.
根據我們獲得的情報
Please don't be trapped by the despair!
請各位不要陷於絕望
The only thing we should do now, is to raise our faces
如今我們該做的 是昂首挺胸
and stand up together!
一起挺直腰板站起來
We can't lose our confidence and give up. We should keep fighting
直到我們
until somebody in the world understands us and takes hands with us.
我們不能消沉不能放棄 要堅持戰鬥到底
What's wrong? What a good baby, it's fine now...
怎麼了 乖寶寶 乖～乖～
In order to make it,
為此
sentikinesis
thymia
I have to rely on the thymia of the Shirushi.
我們必須依仗 各位「印」的情念力
I always wanted to save you from your fates of short-living.
我始終 想要從短命的命運中拯救各位
While I haven't done anything for you...
但是…在我什麼都沒能做到的情況下
I've no choice but to ask you for so much...
還不得不請求各位的幫助
You are the only guy who haven't accept it!
除了你大家早就有這個覺悟了
These guys here have already accepted their curses of short-living for long!
這幫傢伙老早就接受了短命的詛咒
They have also accepted the fate afterwards!
也接受了接下來的命運
If only you can ask us to die for you, it'd be all right!
所以只要你能堂堂正正地 讓我們戰鬥到底就好
Oni?
歐尼？
Do you also...
你也…
willing to help me?
願意幫助我們嗎？
Yes.
是啊
Whew.
哎呀
Shew!
好嘞
Nobody knows whether the route we take is correct.
誰也不可能清楚 我們的道路是不是正確的
But after 4 days, we will face the all-out attack from Skulax.
距離斯奇洛斯的總攻擊還有4天
This is the only thing we are sure...
只有這個 是我們清楚的
The fifth section
第 五 節
I don't want to run away from the hope
第 五 節
乾いた海の跡　望んで
乾いた海の跡　望んで
Staring into the trace of the dried sea
眺望昔日的大海
まだ見ぬ対岸を描く
まだ見ぬ対岸を描く
I will draw the other side I have never seen
描繪未知的彼岸
囚われの心のままなら
囚われの心のままなら
If you remain your heart in captivity
如果囚禁起心靈  一如過往
こんな傷みも知らずにいた
こんな傷みも知らずにいた
You may live without knowing the pain
又怎麼會經歷如此悲傷
美しい詞を告げたひと
美しい詞を告げたひと
The one who told the beautiful story
是誰講述起美好的希望
夜明けも待たずに
夜明けも待たずに
Can not wait for the dawn
讓我等不及黎明
果てのその先を泳ぐ
果てのその先を泳ぐ
Until beyond the end of world, I am swimming
向著天涯海角揚帆起航
虫の唄
虫の唄
Listen to the insects' song
徹夜蟲鳴
眠らず君と聞いた記憶
眠らず君と聞いた記憶
That night is our memory
回憶裡與你一起側耳傾聽
手を　ただ結んで
手を　ただ結んで
Just link hand in hand
只是雙手相牽
半色でも　遠い国でも
半色でも　遠い国でも
No matter it is twilight or a distant country
不論夕陽  還是遠方
短い一章に生まれた夢を
短い一章に生まれた夢を
Born in a short chapter
在這短暫蒼渺的一章裡
抱きしめに行こう
抱きしめに行こう
But let us go and embrace that dream
一起追逐夢想
The sixth section
第 六 節
They may kill somebody tomorrow
或 許 明 天